Guide to the Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1885-2000 UA.40.15
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee Collection
1885-2000
1930-2000
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee
UA.40.15
2 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Lithuanian Nationality Room (LNR) was dedicated on October 4, 1940 becoming the tenth classroom added to the Cathedral of Learning as part of the University of Pittsburgh's Nationality Rooms Program. Located on the first floor, the LNR is used both as a classroom and a space to promote Lithuanian heritage. Under Chairman Peter Pivaronas and Dr. Joseph Baltrusaitis, the Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee was able to design, fund, and construct their classroom in ten years.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following ten series:
Series I: Minutes
Series II: Running Memo
Series III: Financial Statements
Series IV: Lithuanian Nationality Room Correspondence
Series V: Nationality Room Program Correspondence
Series VI: Publicity Materials
Series VII: Oversized Architectural Records
Series VIII: 50th Anniversary
Series IX: Photographic Prints
Series X: Monographs
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Accruals
Further accruals are expected from the ongoing activity of the Committee.
Scope and Content Notes
The Lithuanian Nationality Room Collection is composed of records documenting the planning, design, funding, construction, promotion, and maintenance of the Lithuanian Nationality Room. It also reflects the ongoing activities of the Committee in cultural activities, participation in holiday events and the support of the Lithuanian Room scholarship for study abroad.
History
The Lithuanian Nationality Room (LNR) was the tenth classroom added to the Cathedral of Learning as part of the University of Pittsburgh's Nationality Rooms Program. The Nationality Rooms Program was designed to showcase the history and culture of the various ethnic groups that have come to settle in Pittsburgh and the region. It also seeks to involve the local community with the University through cultural activities and scholarships. Under Chairman Peter Pivaronas and Dr. Joseph Baltruaitis, the LNR Committee was able to design, fund, and construct their classroom in ten years. The development of the Room was coordinated by the first director of the Nationality Rooms, Ruth Crawford Mitchell, and University Architect Albert Klimcheck. Subsequent activities and administrative support have been given the Committee by E. Maxine Bruhns and the office staff.
Funding for the LNR occurred slowly, but relatively smoothly, through vigorous donation drives and outreach to large Lithuanian communities and organizations in Pittsburgh, New York, Baltimore, Chicago and elsewhere but also direct outreach to Lithuania. The design process started in 1935 resulting in two trips to Lithuania for inspiration for the final design. Support came from the Lithuanian government officials and the U.S. envoy, Minister Povilas Žadeikis. Despite some conflict over the final design, it was decided that Antanas Guditis of Lithuania would be the architect, with assistance by Miss Magdalena Avietienaite from Lithuania's Minstry of Foreign Affairs. However, further issues emerged with obtaining Mr. Guditis's final design and in securing room materials (Lithuanian linen and Lithuanian bog soaked oak). Receiving the materials from customs also caused several delays.
In April 1940 all room materials from Lithuania were acquired, and since the majority of the room cost was raised, construction could start. A series of unexpected material shortages in September caused a change in the original room design: M. K. Ciurlionis' "Two Kings" painting was chosen to be recreated as a mural to take the place of the blackboard, the use of black bog oak in furniture designs was extremely limited, and the use of linen as wall coverings reconfigured. Because of these difficulties, the windows and mural were not finished for the October 4, 1940 dedication. The room was officially finished the end of January 1941 after being dogged for months with last minute material and payment issues. Unfortunately, the "Two Kings" mural and linen wall coverings were installed improperly and later needed to be replaced.
Today the LNR, in accordance with the mission statement for the Nationality and Heritage Room Committees, promotes and represents their culture and traditions through events, performances, lectures, films, and exhibits. The LNR Committee also hosts study abroad scholarships for University of Pittsburgh students, and the classroom, a tribute to Lithuanian folk art is used as a learning space for University students day to day.
Separated Material
Oversized Architectural Records are located in map case 26, drawer 1.
Custodial History
In accordance with preserving the activities of each classroom on the Nationality Council, the records of the Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee was collected and maintained by Nationality Rooms Program staff. The early collection was deposited in the University Archives. In 2014 this original collection was combined with the Committees subsequent files and processed in the summer of 2014.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited to the Archives in two separate deposits by the Nationality Rooms Program director.
Correspondence; Architectural drawings (Visual works); University of Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Lithuanian Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Press releases; Photographs; Financial records; Minutes (Administrative records); University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Council; Lithuanian Classroom (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee; Gudaitis, Antanas; Baltrušaitis, Joseph; Čiurlionis, Mikalojus Konstantinas; Pirvaronas, Peter; Bruhns, E. Maxine; Mitchell, Ruth Crawford
- Minutes, 1932-1991; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains the Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee's minutes from the years 1932-1991.
  - 1932-1942 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1961, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Running Memo, 1931-1941; II.
  This series contains records that were created as brief summaries of conferences, correspondence, and events about the Lithuanian Nationality Room for the Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee and the University.
  - 1931-1941 (Box 1, Item 2)
  - Ciurlions, Mykolas Koustantin, circa 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Maironis, Jonas, circa 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Daukantas, Simonas, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kudirka, Vincas, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Duonelaitis, Christian, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Description of Room, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notebook, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1942-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gift and Custodian List, 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Maintenance Handbook, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Memorial, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Member Lists, 1958-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1958, 1977-1984, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lithuanian Exhibit, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lithuanian Panel Plans, post 1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dues, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 50th Anniversary, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Mural, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Financial Statements, 1932-1992; III.
  This series contains records of financial statements pertaining to building costs and Lithuanian Nationality Room event and committee expenses.
  - 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Pertaining to the Lithuanian Room Fund", 1932-1939 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1958, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee Correspondence, 1931-2000; IV.
  This series contains correspondence from the Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee internally, and to Lithuanian Nationality Room Members. The General Correspondence pre 1942 was initially bound with ribbon in cardboard containers in the original 1948 collection. Some materials are in Lithuanian.
  - General Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - General Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - General Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - General Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - General Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - General Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - General Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - General Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - General Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - General Correspondence, 1954-1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence to Members, 1950, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - General Correspondence, 1978-1998 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence to Members, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence to Members, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence to Members, 1991-2000 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Nationality Room Program Correspondence, 1948-1999; V.
  This collection contains correspondence generated by the Nationality Room Program Office pertaining to the LNR. E. Maxine Bruhns and Ruth Crawford Mitchell are the primary authors for the majority of the correspondence. Some materials are in Lithuanian.
  - General Correspondence, 1948-1968 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Mural Redecoration, 1948-1977 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Ciurlionis Paintings, 1955-1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Linen Redecoration, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Linen Redecoration, 1956-1983 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - General Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - General Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Mural Redecoration, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Lithuanian Quasi-Endowment, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - General Correspondence, 1987-1999 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Donations, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Publicity Materials, 1931-2000; VI.
  This series contains publicity materials generated about activities of the Lithuanian Nationality Classroom: newspaper articles, newsletters, magazine articles, event programs, tickets, speeches, and flyers. Events include: dinners, dances, card games, spring luncheon, bake sale, Christmas parties, and committee sponsored trips. Some materials are in Lithuanian.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1931-1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Printed Materials, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Printed Materials, 1937-1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Printed Materials, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Printed Materials, 1950, 1960, 1972-2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dedication, October 4, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Event Transcripts, 1931, 1943, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Event Brochures and Tickets, 1976-1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Event Flyers, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Event Flyers, 1980-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Dr. Landsberg's Event, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Obituaries, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Architectural Records, 1940, 1956, 1962, 1978; VII.
  This series consists of oversized architectural records: room, mural, and furniture designs. There are six items in this series, and they are physically located separate from the rest of the collection in: map case 26, drawer 1.
  - 1940, 1956, 1962, 1978 (Oversize 1)
- 50th Anniversary Album, 1936-1940, 1990; VIII.
  This series is composed of materials that originally made up pages in a 50th Anniversary Album for the Lithuanian Nationality Room.
  - Pages 1-6, 1940, 1990 (Oversize 1, Folder 17)
  - Pages 7-10, circa 1940s (Oversize 1, Folder 18)
  - Pages 12-17, 1940 (Oversize 1, Folder 19)
  - Pages 18-24, 1940 (Oversize 1, Folder 1940)
  - Pages 25-32, 1936, 1940, 1990 (Oversize 1, Folder 21)
- Photographs and Paintings, 1923-1940; IX.
  This series contains photographic and painting prints related to the Lithuanian Nationality Room and Lithuanian heritage. The photographic prints are pictures of the Lithuanian Nationality Room Committee; of the room dedication; of a benefit picnic; of a trip to Kaunas, Lithuania; of the completed room; and of Christmas activities within the room. The painting prints are reproductions of Mikalojus Konstantinas Ciurlionis' work. M. K. Cirulionis created the "Two Kings", which was copied as a mural in the LNR.
  - Finished Room and Original Committee Members Photographs, circa 1940s (Oversize 1, Folder 22)
  - Christmas Photographs, 1940s-1950s, 1979, 1988, 1991-1995 (Oversize 1, Folder 23)
  - Promotion Photographic Prints, circa 1940s, circa 1990s (Oversize 1, Folder 24)
  - Lithuanian Room Slides (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, 1936, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, 1936, 1938, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, October 4, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, 1936, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Black and White Mounted Prints, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Ciurlionis Painting Prints, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    This folder holds "Vasaros naktis ant Nemuno/Summer Night on the Nemunas", "Nerys ties Vilnium/Nerys near Vilnius".
  - Ciurlionis Painting Prints, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    This folder holds "Regejimas Vision" and "Dzuku bajoru kaimelis/Lithunia: a boyer village Dzukija".
- Monographs, 1885-circa 1945; X.
  This series is composed of monographic materials: six books and one album. These materials were donated to the Lithuanian Nationality Room to add to their Lithuanian heritage collection.
  - Dainuokime, undated (Box 3, Item 1)
    This book is written in Lithuanian.
  - Arf Dargis, undated (Box 3, Item 2)
  - M. K. Ciurlionies and Postcards, 1909, 1914, 1927 (Box 3, Item 3)
    The contents of this envelope are written in Lithuanian.
  - Lithuania, My Dear Country, post 1945 (Box 3, Item 4)
    This book is written in English, German, and Lithuanian.
  - Rasztai ir Rasztininkai, 1890 (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Naujas Elementorius, 1901 (Box 3, Item 6)
    This book is accompanied with a notecard that reads: "This primer was the first prize in a competition for best primer in the Lithuanian language. It is the first grammatically (correctly) written primer in Lithuanian written by Antauas Vilkutaitius a popular poet and short story writer--professionally a civil engineer. The primer was published in 1901 at Tilst, East Prussia. When the Lithuanian literature was still forbidden by the Czarist regime in Lithuania." The book is written in Lithuanian.
  - Susivienijimo Lietuviu Amerikoje Auksinio Jubiliejaus Albumas, 1885-1936 (Box 3, Item 7)
    This album is written in Lithuanian.